to understand really what's going on
with faults errors and failures let's
look at an example things always start
with a fault and our fault example is a
programming mistake and let's say that
programming mistake is an add function
that we wrote for our program that works
just fine in all cases except when we
give it to add five and three in which
case it returns seven instead of eight
this type of fault we also call a latent
error it's not really an error until we
do something like this but this type of
a fault we call latent error because
it's only a matter of time when it's
going to be activated so when we
actually execute 5 + 3 and get seven in
some register we now have an error if
the error is a result of some sort of a
latent error like this basically
programming error we say that the fault
has been activated or that we now have
an effective error as opposed to a
latent one in our case we get the
effective error once we call the ad
function with five and three and get
seven instead of eight and then we put
that value in some variable we get a
failure when the system deviates from
specified behavior for example in this
case it might be that the time we were
Computing is the time to schedule a
meeting for and now we schedule a
meeting for 7 instead of 8 as expected
and this is basically the failure of the
system because it didn't effectively
schedule the meeting for when it was
supposed to
it is important to note here that you
need a fault of some sort in order to
get an error but not every fault becomes
an error for the fault of this type for
example to become an error it needs to
be activated we need to actually use the
function in a way that makes it produce
incorrect results even though it always
had the fault it always was faulty in
this way similarly we can have an error
and never get a failure for example here
if this value seven was never used and
programs often do this then we have an
error a variable has the wrong value but
we don't get a failure as a result
another example here would be something
like if we check for example whether
this function returns something larger
than zero then when it returns seven
instead of 8 and we store that in a
register compare it to zero see that
it's still larger than zero now we got
an effective error because a register
held the wrong value but the only thing
we did with this value still cause the
program to function normally so in this
case we have an error but we don't have
a failure